A Guide to the Papers of the Charlottesville Branch of the American Association of University Women, 1955-1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Charlottesville Branch of the American Association of University Women 1955-1993
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6305-f
This collection consists of ca. 1820 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were placed on loan with the Library on September 20, 1995 and were made a gift in 2008 following the dissolution of the Chapter in 2007.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of papers pertaining to the Charlottesville Branch of the American Association of University Women, and includes correspondence, charter and by-laws, meeting minutes, branch reports, treasurer's reports, memorabilia, photographs, printed material and other publications, and a VHS tape.
Correspondence of President Patricia E. Bender discusses topics concerning the Central Virginia Child Development Association, Inc., the University of Virginia Hospital Auxiliary, and the local League of Women Voters, and includes letters from Nancy Douglas Joyner and Roy Land. Correspondence of President Lorie W. Shipe discusses the Soviet Women's Federation of the USSR and the Citizen Ambassador Program of People to People International invitation to visit the Soviet Union and the Virginia Assembly on the Future of Local Government. Correspondence of President Lu Bolen mentions the Advocacy Press and discusses the Association of Virginia Planned Parenthood Affiliates, the support of Senator Tom Michie and the issue of pro-choice. Correspondence of President Wilma W. Albert concerns the University of Virginia Darden School Faculty Committee on the Status of Women and Make Women Count, a political action committee to help elect more women to the Virginia General Assembly. Correspondence of Vice-President Elizabeth R. Schubert mentions a lecture, "Arms Talks between the U. S. A. and the U. S. S. R.," by University of Virginia Professor of Soviet History Woodford McClellan; and, includes letters from Lindsay G. Dorrier, Jr., Commonwealth's Attorney, on his lecture, "Our Local History," and from John Douglas Forbes on his lecture, "Architecture in 19th Century Charlottesville and Its Relation to Romanticism in All the Arts." Correspondence of Vice- President Lu Bolen includes material on the "Development of a Women's Health Knowledge Test" by Susan O. Butler.
Other letters or topics of interest include: letter, September 11, 1986, from Rita Mae Brown concerning an invitation to speak (in History: Charlottesville Branch); University of Virginia Women's Center, FOCUS Women's Resource Center, and Planned Parenthood of the Blue Ridge, Inc. (in Community Services); FOCUS Women's Resource Center and JABA -- Jefferson Area Board for Aging (in Networking Local Organizations); and, memorandum of agreement and papers with the Special Collections Department, corporate representatives Jamie Ferreira and Sybil R. Todd, and the Darden School Faculty Committee on the Status of Women for the study of the "hostile climate" toward women (in University of Virginia).
Contents List
- Adult Day Care 1985-1986, n.d. (Box 1)
- Awards 1991 (Box 1)
- Branch Officers 1981-1993 (Box 1)
- Branch Organization 1980-1991, n.d. (Box 1)
- Branch Presidents 1978-1989, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Frances Christian Brand 1976-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
- Bylaws of the Charlottesville Branch 1977-1993, n.d., (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Bylaws of the Virginia Division 1989-1993, n.d. (Box 1)
- Career Day - Math & Science 1990-1992, n.d. (Box 1)
- Certificates of Merit (blank) n.d. (Box 1)
- Channel One (Whittle) 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Charlottesville Light Opera Company 1955-1979 (Box 2)
- Charter and Bylaws 1971-1989 (Box 2)
- Choices for Tomorrow's Women 1989 (Box 2)
- Community Services 1990-1992, n.d. (Box 2)
- Constructive Conflict Management Seminar 1985 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the President, Patricia E. Bender 1980-1982 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the President, Charlotte Schrader 1983 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the President, Lorie W. Shipe 1988-1991 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the President, Lu Bolen 1991-1992 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Vice-President for Program Development, Wilma W. Albert 1992-1993 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Vice-President for Program Development, Roy Land 1978-1980 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Vice-President for Program Development, Elizabeth R. Schubert 1983-1984 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Vice-President for Program Development, Lorie A. Wierenga 1984-1985 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Vice-President for Program Development, Lu Bolen 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Cultural Interests 1985-1987 (Box 2)
- Division Organization 1989-1992 (Box 2)
- Drunk Driving 1983-1984 (Box 3)
- Education 1984-1986, n.d. (Box 3)
- Education: Local 1976-1993 (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation 1982-1993, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation: Bank Records 1979-1984, n.d. (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation: Calendar Projects 1987-1993, n.d. (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation: Contributions 1990-1992, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation: Correspondence 1982-1992, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Educational Foundation: Fundraising 1987-1991 (Box 4)
- Educational Foundation: Interim Reports 1989-1992 (Box 4)
- Educational Foundation: Receipts 1982-1984 (Box 4)
- Educational Foundation: Reports 1970-1992, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Educational Foundation: Reports - Branch/Division 1972-1981, (8 folders) (Box 4)
- Educational Foundation: Reports - Branch/Division 1981-1988, (11 folders) (Box 5)
- Educational Foundation: Reports - Branch/Division 1988-1990, (4 folders) (Box 6)
- Educational Foundation: Reports - Division 1971-1975 (Box 6)
- Educational Foundation: Research and Project Grants 1972-1976 (Box 6)
- Educational Foundation: Top Ten Branches 1985-1992 (Box 6)
- Environment 1991 (Box 6)
- Equity 1978(1990-1992), (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Graves Analysis: Members 1986-1987 (Box 6)
- Great Decisions 1979-1991, n.d. (Box 6)
- Handbook/Directory of the Charlottesville Branch 1966(1976-1991) (Box 6)
- Handbook/Directory of the Charlottesville Branch: Secretary's File Copies 1977-1987 (Box 6)
- History: Charlottesville Branch 1967(1981-1986), n.d. (Box 7)
- History: National, Division 1957(1973-1988), n.d. (Box 7)
- Insurance: Brochures 1983, n.d. (Box 7)
- International Federation of University Women 1989-1992, n.d. (Box 7)
- Legal Advocacy Fund 1986-1991 (Box 7)
- Legislative Program 1982-1987, n.d. (Box 7)
- Media Collection for the Virginia Division [1976] (Box 7)
- Membership: Lists 1979-1992, n.d. (Box 7)
- Membership: Recruitment 1976-1988, n.d. (Box 7)
- Membership: Recruitment Brochures 1981-1990 (Box 7)
- Minutes of the Charlottesville Branch Board Meetings 1977-1988, (3 folders) (Box 7)
- Minutes of the Charlottesville Branch Board Meetings 1989-1992, n.d. (Box 8)
- Minutes of the Charlottesville Branch Meetings 1962-1992, (4 folders) (Box 8)
- Minutes of the Charlottesville Branch Meetings: Secretary's File 1982-1985 (Box 8)
- Names Honored 1971-1993, (4 folders) (Box 8)
- Names Remembered: Biographical Information 1963-1986 (Box 9)
- Names Remembered Through AAUW Fellowships, Volume II 1970 (Box 9)
- NASA Mailings to Educators 1991-1992, n.d. (Box 9)
- National Conventions 1985-1993 (Box 9)
- National Peace Academy 1984 (Box 9)
- Networking Local Organizations 1983-1990, n.d., (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Newsletters: Branch 1962-1992, (4 folders) (Box 9)
- Newsletters: National 1991-1993 (Box 9)
- Newsletters: National-Leader In Action1985(1991-1993) (Box 10)
- Newsletters: Other Branches' 1981-1993, (2 folders) (Box 10)
- Newsletters: Virginia Division 1985[1992-1993] (Box 10)
- Patient's Bill of Rights 1978-1985, n.d. (Box 10)
- Peace & National Security 1982-1985 (Box 10)
- Photographs 1990-1992, n.d. (Box 10)
- President's Working File ca. 1988-1993 (Box 10)
- Printed Articles 1962-1986 (Box 10)
- Promoting Individual Liberties 1990 (Box 10)
- Publicity 1975-1990,.n.d. (Box 10)
- Public Policy 1984-1993 (Box 10)
- Reports: Centennial Fund Giving 1971-1978 (Box 11)
- Reports: National Branch 1983-1989 (Box 11)
- Resolutions 1984 (Box 11)
- Surveys 1988, 1990, n.d. (Box 11)
- Treasurer's Reports 1984-1992 (Box 11)
- University of Virginia 1984-1993 (Box 11)
- Used Book Sale 1990 (Box 11)
- Virginia Division Convention 1980-1986, (7 folders) (Box 11)
- Virginia Division Convention 1987-1992, (5 folders) (Box 12)
- Virginia Women's Cultural History Project 1983-1984 (Box 12)
- WISEMCO Proposal 1988 (Box 12)
- Women's Coordinating Council 1975-1986, n.d. (Box 12)
- Women's Coordinating Council: Minutes 1976-1981 (Box 12)
- Women's History Week 1982 (Box 12)
- Women's Issues 1984-1986 (Box 12)
- Idealism At Work: Eighty Years of AAUW Fellowships 1967
- Idealism At Work: AAUW Educational Foundation Programs 1967-1981 1981
- Photograph Album -- Some Faces Remembered: Virginia Division AAUW Gatherings n.d.
- AAUW State Convention at Charlottesville, Virginia - Hilton (VHS cassette) 1987